So when the White House was built
عندما بُني البيت الأبيض
in the early 19th century, it was an open house.
في أوائل القرن التاسع عشر كان بيتاً مفتوحاً.
Neighbors came and went. Under President Adams,
يأتيه الجيران و يرحلون. في عهد الرئيس آدمز
a local dentist happened by.
وصل طبيب أسنان محلي بالصدفة.
He wanted to shake the President's hand.
أراد أن يصافح يد الرئيس.
The President dismissed the Secretary of State,
صرف الرئيسُ وزيرَ الخارجية
whom he was conferring with, and asked the dentist
الذي كان يتشاور معه، و سأل الطبيب
if he would remove a tooth.
أن يخلع له ضرسا.
Later, in the 1850s, under President Pierce,
لاحقاً، في غضون 1850، في عهد الرئيس بييرس
he was known to have remarked
كان معروفاً عنه قوله
— probably the only thing he's known for —
- ربما هو الشيء الوحيد المعروف عنه -
when a neighbor passed by and said, "I'd love to see
عندما مر جار وقال: "أود رؤية
the beautiful house," and Pierce said to him,
البيت الجميل" و الرئيس بيرس قال له:
"Why my dear sir, of course you may come in.
"طبعا يا سيدي العزيز، تفضّل بالدخول.
This isn't my house. It is the people's house."
هذا ليس بيتي. إنه بيت الشعب."
Well, when I got to the White House in the beginning
عندما ذهبت إلى البيت الأبيض في أوائل
of 2009, at the start of the Obama Administration,
سنة 2009، في بداية إدارة أوباما،
the White House was anything but open.
البيت الأبيض لم يكن مفتوحًا على الإطلاق.
Bomb blast curtains covered my windows.
ستائر تصد القنابل كانت تغطي نوافذي.
We were running Windows 2000.
كنا نستخدم نظام التشغيل ويندوز 2000.
Social media were blocked at the firewall.
كانت وسائل الإعلام الإجتماعية محجوبة عند الجدار الناري.
We didn't have a blog, let alone a dozen twitter accounts
لم تكن لدينا مدونة، ناهيكم عن عشرات الحسابات في تويتر
like we have today.
كالتي لنا اليوم.
I came in to become the head of Open Government,
أتيت لأصبح رئيسة الحكومة المفتوحة،
to take the values and the practices of transparency,
لأجلب قيم و ممارسات الشفافية،
participation and collaboration, and instill them
و المشاركة و التعاون و ترسيخها
into the way that we work, to open up government,
في أسلوبنا في العمل، لفتح الحكومة
to work with people.
للعمل مع الناس.
Now one of the things that we know
الآن أحد الأمور التي نعرفها
is that companies are very good at getting people to work
هي أن الشركات بارعة في جعل الأشخاص يعملون
together in teams and in networks to make
معًا في فِرق و شبكات لصنع
very complex products, like cars and computers,
منتجات معقدة للغاية، مثل السيارات والحواسيب
and the more complex the products are a society creates,
و كلما زاد تعقيد المنتجات التي يصنعها مجتمعٍ ما
the more successful the society is over time.
كان ذلك المجتمع ناجحًا مع مرور الوقت.
Companies make goods, but governments,
الشركات تصنع السلع ، لكن الحكومات
they make public goods. They work on the cure for cancer
تصنع السلع العامة. إنها تبحث في علاج مرض السرطان
and educating our children and making roads,
و على تعليم أولادنا و إنشاء الطرق
but we don't have institutions that are particularly good
لكن ليست لدينا مؤسسات جيدة بالتحديد
at this kind of complexity. We don't have institutions
في هذا النوع من التعقيد. ليست لدينا مؤسسات
that are good at bringing our talents to bear,
تجيد حشد مواهبنا للاضطلاع
at working with us in this kind of open and collaborative way.
بالعمل معنا بهذ الأسلوب المنفتح التعاونيّ.
So when we wanted to create our Open Government policy,
لذا فعندما أردنا إنشاء سياسة حكومة مفتوحة لنا
what did we do? We wanted, naturally, to ask public sector
ماذا فعلنا؟ أردنا طبعا أن نسأل موظفي القطاع العام
employees how we should open up government.
كيف يجب أن نجعل الحكومة مفتوحة.
Turns out that had never been done before.
تبيّن أن ذلك لم يسبق القيام به من قبل.
We wanted to ask members of the public to help us
أردنا أن نسأل أفرادًا من الجمهور المساعدة
come up with a policy, not after the fact, commenting
على وضع سياسة، ليس بأثر رجعي بالتعليق
on a rule after it's written, the way is typically the case,
على القانون بعد أن يُسنّ كما هو معتاد لدينا
but in advance. There was no legal precedent,
بل استباقيا. لم توجد سابقة قانونية
no cultural precedent, no technical way of doing this.
ولا سابقة ثقافية، و لا مسار إجرائيّ لعمل هذا.
In fact, many people told us it was illegal.
في الواقع، كثيرون أخبرونا أن هذا غير قانوني.
Here's the crux of the obstacle.
هنا أسّ المشكلة.
Governments exist to channel the flow of two things,
توجد الحكومات لتوجيه تدفق شيئين
really, values and expertise to and from government
حقاً: القيم و الخبرات من و إلى الحكومة
and to and from citizens to the end of making decisions.
و من و إلى المواطنين حتى نهاية صنع القرارات.
But the way that our institutions are designed,
لكن الطريقة التي صُممت بها مؤسساتنا
in our rather 18th-century, centralized model,
بنموذج القرن الثامن عشر، المركزي
is to channel the flow of values through voting,
هي أن توجه تدفق القيم بالتصويت.
once every four years, once every two years, at best,
مرة كل أربع سنوات، مرة كل سنتين، أو على الأكثر
once a year. This is a rather anemic and thin way, in this
مرة كل سنة. هذه وسيلة هزيلة و ضعيفة، في حقبة
era of social media, for us to actually express our values.
وسائل الإعلام الإجتماعية، لأن نعبّر بها عن قيمنا.
Today we have technology that lets us express ourselves
لدينا اليوم تكنولوجيا تمكننا من التعبير عن أنفسنا
a great deal, perhaps a little too much.
بدرجة كبيرة، ربما على نحو مبالغ فيه بعض الشيء.
Then in the 19th century, we layer on
ثم في القرن التاسع عشر سَدَلنا فوق ذلك
the concept of bureaucracy and the administrative state
مفهوم البيروقراطية و الدولة الإدارية
to help us govern complex and large societies.
لتتيسر لنا إدارة مجتمعات كبيرة ومعقدة.
But we've centralized these bureaucracies.
لكننا ركّزنا هذه الممارسات البيروقراطية.
We've entrenched them. And we know that
رسخناها. و نحن نعلم أن
the smartest person always works for someone else.
الشخص الأذكى يعمل دوما لحساب شخصٍ آخر.
We need to only look around this room to know that
ما علينا سوى النظر في أرجاء الغرفة لنرى
expertise and intelligence is widely distributed in society,
الذكاء و الخبرة موزعين على نطاق واسع في المجتمع
and not limited simply to our institutions.
و ليسا مقتصرين ببساطة على مؤسساتنا.
Scientists have been studying in recent years
العلماء في السنوات الأخيرة درسوا
the phenomenon that they often describe as flow,
الظاهرة التي غالبًا ما يصفونها بالتدفق
that the design of our systems, whether natural or social,
إن تصميم أنظمتنا، سواء كانت طبيعية أو اجتماعية،
channel the flow of whatever runs through them.
يوجه تدفق كل ما يجري خلالها.
So a river is designed to channel the flow of water,
فالنهر مصمم ليوجه تدفق الماء
and the lightning bolt that comes out of a cloud channels
و الصاعقة التي تأتي من السحب توجّه
the flow of electricity, and a leaf is designed to channel
تدفق الكهرباء، و الورقة مصممة لتوجيه
the flow of nutrients to the tree,
تدفق المغذيات إلى الشجرة.
sometimes even having to route around an obstacle,
أحياناً حتى تضطر للدوران حول عائق ما،
but to get that nutrition flowing.
لأجل أن تتيح للمغذيات التدفق.
The same can be said for our social systems, for our
الشيء ذاته يمكن أن ينطبق على أنظمتنا الإجتماعية، على
systems of government, where, at the very least,
أنظمتنا الحكومية ، حيث، على الأقل،
flow offers us a helpful metaphor for understanding
يقدم لنا التدفق استعارة تساعد على فهم
what the problem is, what's really broken,
المشكلة، و مكمن العطب
and the urgent need that we have, that we all feel today,
و الحاجة الملحة لدينا، التي نشعر بها كلنا اليوم،
to redesign the flow of our institutions.
لإعادة تصميم التدفق في مؤسساتنا.
We live in a Cambrian era of big data, of social networks,
نحن نعيش في عصر كمبري من البيانات الضخمة، و الشبكات الإجتماعية
and we have this opportunity to redesign these institutions
و لدينا الفرصة لإعادة تصميم هذه المؤسسات
that are actually quite recent.
الحديثة في الواقع.
Think about it: What other business do you know,
فكروا بهذا: ما الأعمال الأخرى التي تعرفونها
what other sector of the economy, and especially one
أي قطاع اقتصادي آخر، بالذات قطاع
as big as the public sector, that doesn't seek to reinvent
بحجم القطاع العام، لا يسعى إلى إعادة ابتكار
its business model on a regular basis?
نموذج العمل الخاص به دوريا؟
Sure, we invest plenty in innovation. We invest
بالتأكيد، نحن نستثمر كثيرًا في مجال الابتكار. نحن نستثمر
in broadband and science education and science grants,
في الاتصالات السريعة و تدريس العلوم و في منح دراسة العلوم
but we invest far too little in reinventing and redesigning
لكننا لا نستثمر إلا أقل القليل في إعادة ابتكار و إعادة تصميم
the institutions that we have.
المؤسسات التي لدينا
Now, it's very easy to complain, of course, about
طبعا، من السهل جداً التذمّر من
partisan politics and entrenched bureaucracy, and we love
السياسة الحزبية و البيروقراطية المترسخة، و نحن نحب
to complain about government. It's a perennial pastime,
أن نتذمر من الحكومة. إنها هواية خالدة
especially around election time, but
خاصة قرب مواسم الإنتخابات، لكن
the world is complex. We soon will have 10 billion people,
العالم معقد. قريبًا سنكون 10 مليارات نسمة،
many of whom will lack basic resources.
كثيرون منهم سيفتقرون اللموارد الأساسية.
So complain as we might, what actually can replace
لذا فلنشكي بقدر ما نستطيع، ما الذي يمكن فعليا
what we have today?
أن يحل محل ما لدينا اليوم؟
What comes the day after the Arab Spring?
ماذا سيأتي بعد الربيع العربي؟
Well, one attractive alternative that obviously presents itself
أحد البدائل الجذابة التي تطرح نفسها بوضوح
to us is that of networks. Right? Networks
لنا هي الشبكات الإجتماعية. أليس كذلك؟ شبكات
like Facebook and Twitter. They're lean. They're mean.
مثل فيس بوك و تويتر. إنها رشيقة. إنها مؤثرة.
You've got 3,000 employees at Facebook
هناك 3.000 موظف يعملون في شبكة الفيس بوك
governing 900 million inhabitants.
يحكمون 900 مليون شخص.
We might even call them citizens, because they've recently
يمكننا كذلك تسميتهم بالمواطنين، لأنهم حالياً
risen up to fight against legislative incursion,
نهضوا لمقاومة الهجوم التشريعي،
and the citizens of these networks work together
و مواطنو تلك الشبكات يعملون معًا
to serve each other in great ways.
لخدمة بعضهم البعض بطرق رائعة.
But private communities, private, corporate,
لكن المجتمعات الخاصة و الشركات الخاصة
privatizing communities, are not bottom-up democracies.
التي تخصخص المجتمعات، ليست ديموقراطيات جذرية.
They cannot replace government.
لا يمكنها أن تحل محل الحكومة.
Friending someone on Facebook is not complex enough
مصادقة شخص ما على الفيس بوك ليس معقدًا بما يكفي
to do the hard work of you and I collaborating
ليحل محل العمل الشاق في تعاوننا
with each other and doing the hard work of governance.
مع بعضنا لأداء العمل الشاق للحوكمة.
But social media do teach us something.
لكن وسائل الإعلام الاجتماعية تعلّمنا شيئاً ما:
Why is Twitter so successful? Because it opens up its platform.
لماذا موقع تويتر ناجح هكذا؟ لإنه يجعل منصته مفتوحة.
It opens up the API to allow hundreds of thousands
إنه يفتح واجهة برمجية للتطبيقات ليسمح لمئات الألوف
of new applications to be built on top of it, so that we can
من التطبيقات الجديدة بأن تنبني فوقه، بحيث يمكننا
read and process information in new and exciting ways.
قراءة و معالجة المعلومات بطرق جديدة مثيرة.
We need to think about how to open up the API
نحتاج أن نفكر في كيفية فتح واجهة برمجة التطبيقات
of government, and the way that we're going to do that,
الخاصة بالحكومة، و الطريقة التي سننفذ بها ذلك.
the next great superpower is going to be the one
القوة العظمى القادمة ستكون من
who can successfully combine the hierarchy of institution --
يستطيع أن يزاوج بنجاح تراتبية المؤسسات --
because we have to maintain those public values,
لأننا يجب أن نحافظ على تلك القيم العامة
we have to coordinate the flow -- but with the diversity
و علينا أن ننسق التدفق -- لكن مع التنوع
and the pulsating life and the chaos and the excitement
و الحياة النابضة و الفوضى و الإثارة
of networks, all of us working together to build
التي تميز الشبكات الاجتماعية، جميعنا نعمل معًا لبناء
these new innovations on top of our institutions,
تلك الابتكارات الجديدة فوق مؤسساتنا
to engage in the practice of governance.
للمشاركة في ممارسة الحوكمة.
We have a precedent for this. Good old Henry II here,
لدينا سابقة لهذا. الملك هنري الثاني طيب الذكر،
in the 12th century, invented the jury.
في القرن الثاني عشر، ابتكر هيئة المحلفين.
Powerful, practical, palpable model for handing power
نموذج واضح وعملي وقوي لتسليم السلطة
from government to citizens.
من الحكومة إلى المواطنين.
Today we have the opportunity, and we have
اليوم أمامنا فرصة، و لدينا
the imperative, to create thousands of new ways
دافع، لخلق آلاف الوسائل الجديدة
of interconnecting between networks and institutions,
للربط بين الشبكات و المؤسسات،
thousands of new kinds of juries: the citizen jury,
آلاف الأنواع الجديدة لهيئة المحلفين: هيئة محلفي المواطنين،
the Carrotmob, the hackathon, we are just beginning
Carrotmob، و الهاكثونات، نحن على أوّل الطريق
to invent the models by which we can cocreate
لابتكار نماذج تمكننا من التعاون
the process of governance.
في صيرورة الحوكمة.
Now, we don't fully have a picture of what this will look like
ليست لدينا صورة كاملة عما سيبدو عليه ذلك
yet, but we're seeing pockets of evolution
حتى الآن، لكننا نرى جيوبا من التطوّر
emerging all around us -- maybe not even evolution,
تبرز حولنا -- قد لايكون تطوّرا
I'd even start to call it a revolution -- in the way that we govern.
بل إني لأسميها ثورة -- في الطريقة التي نحكم بها.
Some of it's very high-tech,
بعضها ذات تقنية رفيعة للغاية
and some of it is extremely low-tech,
و بعضها ذات تقنية خفيضة للغاية
such as the project that MKSS is running in Rajasthan,
مثل المشروع الذي تديره منظمة MKSS في راجستان
India, where they take the spending data of the state
في الهند، حيث يقومون بجمع بيانات إنفاق حكومة الولاية
and paint it on 100,000 village walls,
و ينشرونها على 100.000 جدار في القرى،
and then invite the villagers to come and comment
ثم يدعون سكان القرى ليأتون ويعلقوا على
who is on the government payroll, who's actually died,
من في جداول رواتب الحكومة وهو في الحقيقة ميت،
what are the bridges that have been built to nowhere,
ما الجسور التي بُنيت لتفضي إلى لا مكان،
and to work together through civic engagement to save
و ليعملوا معًا من خلال المشاركة المدنية ليحافظوا
real money and participate and have access to that budget.
على المال الحقيقي و يشتركوا ويحصلوا على تلك الميزانية.
But it's not just about policing government.
لكن الأمر لا يتعلق فقط بضبط الحكومة.
It's also about creating government.
إنه يتعلق أيضاً بخلق الحكومة.
Spacehive in the U.K. is engaging in crowd-funding,
Spacehive في المملكة المتحدة تعمل على حشد التمويل
getting you and me to raise the money to build
تتيح لي ولكم بجمع المال لبناء
the goalposts and the park benches that will actually
قوائم المرمى و الكراسي في الحدائق العامة التي
allow us to deliver better services in our communities.
ستوصل خدمات أفضل لمجتمعاتنا.
No one is better at this activity of actually getting us
لا يوجد من هو أفضل في هذا النشاط الذي يسمح لنا
to engage in delivering services,
بالمشاركة في تقديم الخدمات
sometimes where none exist, than Ushahidi.
غير المتوفرة أحياناً، أكثر من نظام أشاهدي.
Created after the post-election riots in Kenya in 2008,
نظام تأسس بعد أعمال الشغب التي أعقبت الانتخابات في كينيا في 2008
this crisis-mapping website and community is actually able
كموقع وِب معني برسم خرائط الأزمات، و هو في الواقع يمَكّننا
to crowdsource and target the delivery of
من جمع المعلومات بالحشد بهدف تقديم
better rescue services to people trapped under the rubble,
خدمات إنقاذ أفضل للأشخاص المحاصرين تحت الأنقاض
whether it's after the earthquakes in Haiti,
سواء بعد الزلازل في هاييتي
or more recently in Italy.
أو مؤخرا في إيطاليا.
And the Red Cross too is training volunteers and Twitter
و الصليب الأحمر كذلك يدرب متطوعين، وموقع تويتر
is certifying them, not simply to supplement existing
يعتمدهم، ليس و حسب ليعضدوا عمل المؤسسات
government institutions, but in many cases, to replace them.
الحكومية القائمة، بل في حالات كثيرة، لتحل محلها.
Now what we're seeing lots of examples of, obviously,
نرى الآن أمثلة كثيرة، واضحة،
is the opening up of government data,
على انفتاح البيانات الحكومية.
not enough examples of this yet, but we're starting
ليست أمثلة كافية على ذلك حتى الآن، لكننا بدأنا
to see this practice of people creating and generating
نرى هذه الممارسة لأشخاص ينشئون و يصنعون
innovative applications on top of government data.
تطبيقات مبتكرة على أساس البيانات الحكومية
There's so many examples I could have picked, and I
توجد أمثلة كثيرة يمكنني الانتقاء منها
selected this one of Jon Bon Jovi. Some of you
و سأختار مثال جون بون جوفي:
may or may not know that he runs a soup kitchen
بعضكم يعرف أنه يدير مطعم حساء
in New Jersey, where he caters to and serves the homeless
في نيوجرسي، حيث يطعم المشردين و يخدمهم
and particularly homeless veterans.
خاصة قدامى المحاربين المشردين.
In February, he approached the White House, and said,
في فبراير، اتصل بالبيت الأبيض و قال:
"I would like to fund a prize to create scalable national
"أود التبرع بجائزة لإنشاء تطبيقات وطنية قابلة للتطوير
applications, apps, that will help not only the homeless
من شأنها أن تساعد ليس المشردين و حسب
but those who deliver services [to] them to do so better."
بل كذلك أولئك الذين يخدمونهم كي يقوموا بذلك على نحو أفضل"
February 2012 to June of 2012,
بين فبراير 2012 و يونيو 2012
the finalists are announced in the competition.
تم الإعلان عن الفائزين في المسابقة.
Can you imagine, in the bureaucratic world of yesteryear,
هل خطر في بالكم، في عالم الأمس البيروقراطي، أنه يمكن
getting anything done in a four-month period of time?
إنجاز أي شيء خلال أربعة أشهر؟
You can barely fill out the forms in that amount of time,
بالكاد يمكنكم تعبئة الاستمارات في تلك المدة
let alone generate real, palpable innovations
ناهيكم عن إنتاج ابتكارات حقيقية و ملموسة
that improve people's lives.
من شأنها أن تحسّن حياة الناس.
And I want to be clear to mention that this open government
و أريد أن أكون واضحة في بيان أن ثورة الحكومة المفتوحة
revolution is not about privatizing government,
هذه لا تتعلق بخصخصة الحكومة
because in many cases what it can do when we have
ففي حالات كثيرة عندما تكون لدينا إرادة
the will to do so is to deliver more progressive
لفعل ذلك فإن ما ينتج هو سياسة أكثر تقدميّة أفضل
and better policy than the regulations and the legislative
من التنظيمات و استراتيجيات التشريع
and litigation-oriented strategies
القائمة على التقاضي
by which we make policy today.
التي نطوّر بها سياساتنا اليوم.
In the State of Texas, they regulate 515 professions,
في ولاية تكساس ينظمّون 515 مهنة
from well-driller to florist.
من حفاري الآبار إلى بائعي الزهور.
Now, you can carry a gun into a church in Dallas,
معروف أن بوسعكم الدخول بأسلحتكم إلى الكنائس في دَلاس
but do not make a flower arrangement without a license,
لكن لا ترتكبوا تنسيق الزهور بلا رخصة
because that will land you in jail.
لأن ذلك سيدخلكم السجن.
So what is Texas doing? They're asking you and me,
فما الذي تفعله تكساس؟ إنهم يطلبون منكم و مني
using online policy wikis, to help not simply get rid of
استخدام ويكيات السياسات لنساعد ليس و حسب في التخلص
burdensome regulations that impede entrepreneurship,
من التنظيمات المرهقة التي تعيق ريادة الأعمال
but to replace those regulations with more innovative
بل لاستبدال تلك التنظيمات ببدائل أكثر ابتكارًا
alternatives, sometimes using transparency in the creation
أحيانًا باستخدام الشفافية في بناء
of new iPhone apps that will allows us
تطبيقات آيفون جديدة تمكننا
both to protect consumers and the public
من حماية المستهلكين و العامة
and to encourage economic development.
و تشجيع النمو الاقتصادي.
That is a nice sideline of open government.
هذا جانب لطيف من الحكومة المفتوحة.
It's not only the benefits that we've talked about with regard
ليست و حسب الفوائد التي تناولناها فيما يتعلق
to development. It's the economic benefits and the
بالتنمية، بل كذلك الفوائد الاقتصادية
job creation that's coming from this open innovation work.
و خلق فرص العمل التي تتأتى من هذا العمل المفتوح الابتكاري.
Sberbank, the largest and oldest bank in Russia,
Sberbank، أكبر و أقدم مصرف في روسيا
largely owned by the Russian government,
الذي تملك أغلبه الحكومة الروسية
has started practicing crowdsourcing, engaging
بدأ ممارسة حشد المصادر بإشراك
its employees and citizens in the public in developing innovations.
موظفيه و عامة المواطنين في تطوير الابتكارات.
Last year they saved a billion dollars, 30 billion rubles,
فوفروا السنة الماضية مليار دولار، أي 30 مليار روبل
from open innovation, and they're pushing radically
بالابتكار المفتوح، وهم يدفعون براديكالية في اتجاه
the extension of crowdsourcing, not only from banking,
التوسع في حشد المصادر، ليس حصرا من القطاع المصرفي
but into the public sector.
بل كذلك في القطاع العام.
And we see lots of examples of these innovators using
نرى أمثلة كثيرة لأولئك المبتكرين الذين يستخدمون
open government data, not simply to make apps,
بيانات الحكومة المفتوحة، ليس لمجرد إنشاء تطبيقات،
but then to make companies and to hire people
بل لاحقًا لتأسيس شركات و توظيف الناس
to build them working with the government.
لتطوير تلك التطبيقات بالعمل مع الحكومة.
So a lot of these innovations are local.
الكثير من هذه الابتكارات محليّ.
In San Ramon, California, they published an iPhone app
في مدينة سان رامون في ولاية كاليفورنيا، نشروا تطبيق آيفون
in which they allow you or me to say we are certified
يتيحون فيه لكم أو لي بالإقرار عن أننا نحوز شهادة
CPR-trained, and then when someone has a heart attack,
تدريب على الإنعاش القلبي، ثُم عندما يُصاب شخص ما بنوبة قلبية
a notification goes out so that you
يصدر تنبيه كي يتسنى لكم
can rush over to the person over here and deliver CPR.
الهرع إلى حيث ذلك الشخص لإسعافه.
The victim who receives bystander CPR
الضحية التي تتلقى إنعاشا قلبيا من المارة
is more than twice as likely to survive.
تتضاعف أكثر من مرتين فرصة بقاءه حيا
"There is a hero in all of us," is their slogan.
"يوجد بطل في داخل كلٍ منا" هو شعارهم.
But it's not limited to the local.
لكن هذا لا يقتصر على المستوى المحلي.
British Columbia, Canada, is publishing a catalogue
ولاية كولومبيا البريطانية في كندا تنشر دليلا
of all the ways that its residents and citizens can engage
يسرد كل الطرق الي يمكن بها للمواطنين و المقيمين
with the state in the cocreation of governance.
المشاركة مع الولاية في الحوكمة.
Let me be very clear,
دعوني أكون واضحة للغاية
and perhaps controversial,
وربما مثيرة للجدل
that open government is not
الحكومة المفتوحة ليست
about transparent government.
الحكومة الشفافة.
Simply throwing data over the transom doesn't change
نشر البيانات عل الملأ وحده لا يغير
how government works.
الطريقة التي تعمل بها الحكومة.
It doesn't get anybody to do anything with that data
و لا يتيح لأيِ كان بفعل أي شيء بتلك البيانات
to change lives, to solve problems, and it doesn't change
بما يغيّر حياة الآخرين، ويحل المشكلات، و هو لا يغيّر
government.
الحكومة.
What it does is it creates an adversarial relationship
ما يؤدي إليه نشر البيانات هو خلق تنازع
between civil society and government
بين المجتمع المدني و الحكومة
over the control and ownership of information.
حول السيطرة على المعلومات و حيازتها.
And transparency, by itself, is not reducing the flow
و الشفافية، بحد ذاتها، لا تقلل تدفق
of money into politics, and arguably,
المال إلى السياسة، و تمكننا المحاجاة
it's not even producing accountability as well as it might
أنها حتى لا تؤدي إلى المساءلة كما ينبغي لها
if we took the next step of combining participation and
لو أخذنا الخطوة التالية بمزاوجة المشاركة
collaboration with transparency to transform how we work.
و التعاون بالشفافية لتحويل أسلوب عملنا
We're going to see this evolution really in two phases,
فسنرى تطورًا حقيقيا على مرحلتين
I think. The first phase of the open government revolution
كما أظن. المرحلة الأولى لثورة الحكومة المفتوحة
is delivering better information from the crowd
تقدم بيانات أفضل من طرف الجماهير
into the center.
إلى المركز.
Starting in 2005, and this is how this open government
بدءًا من 2005، و هذه قصة بداية العمل على الحكومة المفتوحة
work in the U.S. really got started,
فعليا في الولايات المتحدة،
I was teaching a patent law class to my students and
كنت أُدرس مادة قانون براءات الإختراع لطلابي
explaining to them how a single person in the bureaucracy
و أشرح لهم كيف أن فردا واحدا في البيروقراطية
has the power to make a decision
لديه القوة اتخاذ القرار
about which patent application becomes the next patent,
في أي طلبات براءة الاختراع سيصير براءة الإختراع المقبلة
and therefore monopolizes for 20 years the rights
و بالتالي احتكارا لمدة عشرين سنة للحقوق
over an entire field of inventive activity.
في حقل كامل من النشاط الابتكاري.
Well, what did we do? We said, we can make a website,
حسناً، ماذا فعلنا؟ قلنا، يمكننا أن ننشئ موقع وِب
we can make an expert network, a social network,
يمكننا أن ننشئ شبكة خبراء، شبكة اجتماعية
that would connect the network to the institution
لها أن تربط الشبكة بالمؤسسة
to allow scientists and technologists to get
لتتيح للعلماء و التقنيين بتزويد
better information to the patent office
معلومات أفضل إلى مكتب براءات الاختراع
to aid in making those decisions.
للمساعدة في اتخاذ تلك القرارات.
We piloted the work in the U.S. and the U.K. and Japan
قمنا بتجربة العمل في الولايات المتحدة و المملكة المتحدة و اليابان
and Australia, and now I'm pleased to report
و أستراليا، و الآن يسعدني القول
that the United States Patent Office will be rolling out
أن مكتب براءات الاختراع في الولايات المتحدة سيُحقق
universal, complete, and total openness,
انفتاحًا عالميًا تاما شاملا
so that all patent applications will now be open
كي تصير كل طلبات براءة الاختراع مفتوحة
for citizen participation, beginning this year.
لمشاركة المواطنين، ابتداءً من هذه السنة.
The second phase of this evolution — Yeah. (Applause)
المرحلة الثانية من هذا التطور - نعم. (تصفيق)
They deserve a hand. (Applause)
يستحقون التحية (تصفيق)
The first phase is in getting better information in.
المرحلة الأولى تتعلق بإدخال معلومات أفضل.
The second phase is in getting decision-making power out.
المرحلة الثانية تتعلق بنقل سلطة صنع القرار إلى الخارج.
Participatory budgeting has long been practiced
الميزانية التشاركية تُطبّق منذ وقت طويل
in Porto Alegre, Brazil.
في بورتو أليغري في البرازيل.
They're just starting it in the 49th Ward in Chicago.
و قد للتو تطبيقها في حيّ "وارد 49" في شيكاغو.
Russia is using wikis to get citizens writing law together,
روسيا تستخدم نُظُم الويكي لتُمكن المواطنين من كتابة القانون سويًا
as is Lithuania. When we start to see
كذلك في ليتوانيا. عندما تترائى لنا
power over the core functions of government
السلطة على المهام الرئيسية للحكومة
— spending, legislation, decision-making —
- الإنفاق، و التشريع، و اتخاذ القرار -
then we're well on our way to an open government revolution.
فإننا نكون على الطريق الصحيح إلى ثورة الحكومة المفتوحة.
There are many things that we can do to get us there.
يوجد الكثير مما يمكننا فعله لنحقق ذلك.
Obviously opening up the data is one,
طبعا، فتح البيانات أحدها
but the important thing is to create lots more --
لكن المهم هو إتاحة الكثير--
create and curate -- lots more participatory opportunities.
إتاحة و اجتذاب -- الكثير من فرص المشاركة.
Hackathons and mashathons and working with data
استخدام الهاكثونات والماشاثونات للعمل على البيانات
to build apps is an intelligible way for people to engage
لبناء التطبيقات أسلوب مفهوم للناس لينخرطوا
and participate, like the jury is,
و يشاركوا، كما هو الحال مع المحلفين
but we're going to need lots more things like it.
لكننا سنحتاج إلى أشياء كثيرة مثل ذلك.
And that's why we need to start with our youngest people.
و هذا هو السبب في أن علينا البدء بصغارنا.
We've heard talk here at TED about people
لقد استمعنا إلى محاضرات هنا في TED عن أشخاص
biohacking and hacking their plants with Arduino,
يخترقون نباتاتهم حيويًا بالأردوينو
and Mozilla is doing work around the world in getting
و شركة موزيلا تعمل حول العالم على
young people to build websites and make videos.
تحفيز الشباب لبناء مواقع وِب و مقاطع الفيديو.
When we start by teaching young people that we live,
عندما نشرع في تعليم الناشئين أننا لا نعيش
not in a passive society, a read-only society,
في مجتمع سلبي، مجتمع للمطالعة فقط
but in a writable society, where we have the power
بل في مجتمع قابل للتعديل، حيث لدينا لقوة
to change our communities, to change our institutions,
لتغيير مجتمعاتنا، لتغيير مؤسساتنا
that's when we begin to really put ourselves on the pathway
فحينها نبدأ حقًا بوضع أنفسنا على الطريق
towards this open government innovation,
نحو ابتكار الحكومة المفتوحة هذه
towards this open government movement,
نحو حركة الحكومة المفتوحة هذه
towards this open government revolution.
نحو ثورة الحكومة المفتوحة هذه
So let me close by saying that I think the important thing
دعوني أختم بقولي إن المهم في رأيي
for us to do is to talk about and demand this revolution.
فعله هو أن الحديث عن هذه الثورة و المطالبة بها.
We don't have words, really, to describe it yet.
ليست لدينا بعد، حقيقةً، كلمات لوصفها.
Words like equality and fairness and the traditional
الكلمات مثل "المساواة" و "العدالة" و الانتخابات
elections, democracy, these are not really great terms yet.
التقليدية، و الديموقراطية، لم تصبح بعد كلمات عظيمة.
They're not fun enough. They're not exciting enough
ليست لطيفة بما يكفي، و ليست مثيرة بما يكفي
to get us engaged in this tremendous opportunity
لدفعنا إلى لانخراط في هذه الفرصة الهائلة
that awaits us. But I would argue that if we want to see
التي تسنح لنا. لكني أحاجج بأننا إن أردنا أن نرى
the kinds of innovations, the hopeful and exciting
نوعية الابتكارات، و الأفكار الواعدة المثيرة
innovations that we hear talked about here at TED,
التي نسمع المحاضرات عنها هنا في TED
in clean energy, in clean education,
حول الطاقة النظيفة، و التعليم النظيف
in development, if we want to see those adopted
و التنمية؛ إن أردنا أن نرى هذه الأفكار متبناة
and we want to see those scaled,
و أن نرى هذه الأفكار منتشرة
we want to see them become the governance of tomorrow,
و أن نراها تصبح حَوكمة المستقبل
then we must all participate,
فعلينا جميعاً أن نشارك
then we must get involved.
فعلينا أن ننخرط.
We must open up our institutions, and like the leaf,
علينا أن نفتح مؤسساتنا، و مثل الورقة
we must let the nutrients flow throughout our body politic,
علينا أن نجعل المُغذيات تتدفق خلال جسدنا السياسي
throughout our culture, to create open institutions
و خلال ثقافتنا، لصنع مؤسسات مفتوحة
to create a stronger democracy, a better tomorrow.
لصنع ديموقراطية أقوى، و غد أفضل.
Thank you. (Applause)
شكراً (تصفيق)